A Guide to the Atcheson L. Hench Autograph Collection
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series II: Collection of Modern Autographs
  - 1921 October 21 Oscar W. Underwood (1862-1929) to Waldo C. Moore, The Peoples Banking Company, Lewisburg, Ohio, reluctantly complies with his request for a check for one cent to be used as an exhibit at the convention of the Ohio Bankers Association, 1 typewritten page (6435-l) (Box-folder 11:108)
  - 1923 December 15 Oscar W. Underwood (1862-1929) to H.C. Newcomb, thanks him for sending the news article from The New York Times concerning the two-thirds rule in the national Democratic conventions, 1 typewritten page (6435-av) (Box-folder 11:109)
  - 1921 November 26 Oscar W. Underwood (1862-1929) to Richard V. Oulahan, thanks him for the kindly words written about himself in Oulahan's article in Current History, 1 typewritten page (6435-ak) (Box-folder 11:110)
  - 1914 April 13 Oscar W. Underwood (1862-1929) to Miss Elizabeth Patten, thanks her for her letter of congratulations upon his victory in the senatorial primary election in Alabama, 1 typewritten page (6435-ak) (Box-folder 11:111)
  - 1922 June 17 Oscar W. Underwood (1862-1929) to C.M. Sheridan, declines to send him his favorite cooking recipe as he has none, 1 typewritten page (6435-l) (Box-folder 11:112)
  - 1925 June 3 Oscar W. Underwood (1862-1929) to "Dear Claude" [Swanson?], agrees to vote for Ed Halsey to succeed Mr. Keller, 1 typewritten page (6435-ak) (Box-folder 11:113)
  - 1922 June 20 Oscar W. Underwood (1862-1929) to Everett P. Wheeler (1840-1925), believes the Republican Party is mistaken in attempting to pass the highest tariff bill they have ever proposed, 1 typewritten page (6435-t) (Box-folder 11:114)
  - 1922 Oscar W. Underwood (1862-1929) Correspondence with Warren G. Harding concerning a proposed Supreme Court appointment for Underwood, 2 copies (6435-bg) (Box-folder 11:115)
  - n.d. Dr. James Van Allen (1914-?) Autograph on a cartoon about the Van Allen Belts (6435-be) (Box-folder 12:1)
  - 1861 May 29 Virginia and Tennessee Railroad Company Receipt (6435-bg) (Box-folder 12:2)
  - 1903 July 30 Cosima Wagner (1837-1930), daughter of Franz Liszt, second wife of the German composer, Richard Wagner, and director of the Bayreuth Festival from 1883-1906, to [Dear Esteemed Sir?], thanks her unknown gentleman correspondent for being of assistance to her son, Siegfried, who regards him with the highest honor and respect, 3 pages on 1 l., in German (6435-az) (Box-folder 12:3)
  - 1886 August 10 James A. Walker (1832-1901), Wytheville, Virginia lawyer and former member of the "Stonewall Brigade" during the Civil War, to W.P. Hopkins, sends his photograph and furnishes some biographical information, particularly about his Civil War service, 2 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 12:4)
  - 1797 July 6 Elizabeth (Foote) Washington (d. 1812), wife of Lund Washington (d. 1796), giving power of attorney to her nephew, William Hayward Foote, witnessed by James A. Sutton & Cleon Moore, 1 page (6435-w) (Box-folder 12:5)
  - [1890 December] George Washington Estate - two form letters on the stationery of Mitchell's Rare and Standard Books, Broadway, New York, documenting the authenticity of two items (not present) purchased by Mitchell's from a sale of relics formerly belonging to the estate of George Washington and currently from the estate of Mrs. Lorenzo Lewis and signed by the administrator of her estate, H.L. D. Lewis. The sale was held at Messrs. Birch's of Philadelphia in December 1890. These sale items include a release in the handwriting of General Washington and a lease between Charles West and General Washington, in his handwriting. 2 items, signed by H.L.D. Lewis (6435) (Box-folder 12:6)
  - 1872 March 11 Edwin Percy Whipple (1819-1886) to [Paul Hamilton] Hayne (1830-1886), writes that he is very happy that Hayne will receive a highly complimentary notice in the April number of The Atlantic for his latest volume of poems, 2 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 12:7)
  - 1880 March 28 Edwin Percy Whipple (1819-1886) to "Dear Moore," discusses Sir William Jones (1746-1794) and the concept of "Sovereign Law" as dominant over thrones and kings, if used with discretion, mentions several political examples, including the administration of Chatham [William Pitt] dispensing with the revenue laws in opening the ports during a scarcity of corn production as an example in Great Britain; the current disagreement between William Evert Gladstone and Benjamin Disraeli over getting England into complications with foreign states; and the danger of using the concept to put down insurrections anywhere in Europe following the defeat of Napoleon, 4 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 12:8)
  - 1846 July 16 Edwin Percy Whipple (1819-1886) to Jeremiah [Verne?], furnishes the titles of his lectures, "Wit and Humor" and "Authors in their Relations to Life", 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 12:9)
  - 1853 June 8 Edwin Percy Whipple (1819-1886) to "Dear Sir" believes he is to lecture in his city during the next season at the Lyceum and is willing to talk to his association if there is no rivalry between the two groups, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 12:10)
  - 1859 November 8 Edwin Percy Whipple (1819-1886) to "Dear Sir" sends his travel plans, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 12:11)
  - 1868 November 18 Edwin Percy Whipple (1819-1886) signature endorsing a check drawn on the National Bank of Boston from his publisher, Fields, Osgood & Co., endorsed check (6435-az) (Box-folder 12:12)
  - 1840 July 6 Thomas Willis White (1788-1843), owner and publisher of the Southern Literary Messenger to Lewis Jacob Cist (1818-1885), writes that he likes his writing very much and that he has included lighter material in his magazine as he has "empty heads as well as wise ones to deal with", 1 page (6435-a) (Box-folder 12:13)
  - [1878] September 11 George John Whyte-Melville to "My dear Chapman, [Frederic?] Chapman, of Chapman and Hall publishers, discusses the terms for publication of Roy's Wife a novel published in two volumes in 1878, 3 pages on 1 l. (6435-a) (Box-folder 12:14)
  - 1817 July 9 William Wilkins (1779-1865), Bank of Pittsburgh, Secretary of War under Tyler, to G.A. Werth, informs him that his wife and children are well, will purchase a flat boat and will leave on Monday next, and asks him to collect the enclosed bills for him, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 12:15)
  - [post 1846] Cornelia Grinnell Willis, second wife of Nathaniel Parker Willis, to "General Morris" [George Pope Morris?], sends a few bits for the Home Journal as promised, and asks him to forward mail to Willis in Toronto, 2 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 12:16)
  - n.y. October 10 Nathaniel Parker Willis (1806-1867) to Carey & Hart, Publishers, has sent them the autograph to copy as requested, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 12:17)
  - n.d. Nathaniel Parker Willis (1806-1867) to [M.J. Cohen?], regrets that he is unable to dine with him due to a prior commitment, 2 pages on 1 l. with typed transcript copy (6435) (Box-folder 12:18)
  - n.d. Nathaniel Parker Willis (1806-1867) to Miss Derby, sends her a memento, a "thin octavo" to read, of time spent pleasurably in her company, 2 pages of penciled [draft] on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 12:19)
  - n.d. Nathaniel Parker Willis (1806-1867) to "Dear Mr. Harold," offers one of his brochures about the men, improvements, etc. of Trenton, New Jersey, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 12:20)
  - 1847 December 1 Nathaniel Parker Willis (1806-1867) to A. Hart, sends his correspondence with Lindsay & Blakiston who have refused to settle with him, forcing him to turn it over to lawyers in Philadelphia to settle the matter, 2 pages on 1 l., with typed transcript (6435) (Box-folder 12:21)
  - 1863 October 8 Nathaniel Parker Willis (1806-1867) to Ira F. Hart, declines his invitation to lecture due the long journey involved, explaining his willingness to lecture at Albany and Troy as due to the high price offered for each lecture ($75.00) and both involving just a single trip, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 12:22)
  - 1851 January 17 Nathaniel Parker Willis (1806-1867) to Mr. Hirst, apologizes for the delay in his response, and writes concerning the work of Mrs. Hirst, "I think Mrs. Hirst a most remarkable inventor of plot, & with a kind of talent that would do wonders in play-writing. Her language is still too youthfully over-colored for the present taste of plain narrative. The stories I send back to you are full of talent & promise & would sell anywhere, but better if trimmed & simplified in the language only." He also explains the Home Journal rule of publishing "no original matter which should put us under any obligation ever of courtesy.", 3 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 12:23)
  - 1857 March 17 Nathaniel Parker Willis (1806-1867) to Mrs. Holland, promises to make mention of her excellent plan in The Home Journal, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 12:24)
  - 1861 November 19 Nathaniel Parker Willis (1806-1867) to "My dear Ida," expresses his thankfulness that her father's health is improving, sends copy for the "Prospectus for 1862" for her to read to her father for his approval, and mentions that Nellie and Imogen are currently in New York, 2 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 12:25)
  - n.d. Nathaniel Parker Willis (1806-1867) to "Dear Morris" [George Pope Morris?], writes that he has signed the paper and asks, "What does the "Gentlemen" mean, put at the beginning of a letter from a friend, & "not intended for publication?" presumably from one of their authors, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 12:26)
  - n.d. Nathaniel Parker Willis (1806-1867) to Mr. Sprague, regrets that due to pressing business, he feels unable to breakfast with him tomorrow, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 12:27)
  - n.y. September 19 Nathaniel Parker Willis (1806-1867) to "My dear Stoddard," promises to do what he wishes although his hand is still so swollen "from my horse throwing" that he is writing with a crippled fist, 1 page formerly pasted on the flyleaf (now detached) of The Poems, Sacred, Passionate, and Humorous of Nathaniel Parker Willis (6435) (Box-folder 12:28)
  - [1828?] February Nathaniel Parker Willis (1806-1867), Boston, to Colonel John B. Van Schaick, Albany, writes that he would have come to visit him in Albany, except that the immediate publication of The Legendary prevented him. The Legendary was an early attempt to promote American authors, edited by N.P. Willis and published by Samuel Goodrich, only for one year., 2 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 12:29)
  - [1828?] April 13 Nathaniel Parker Willis (1806-1867), Boston, to Colonel John B. Van Schaick, Albany, refers to Samuel Goodrich, discusses their romantic interests and his own awkward correspondence with "Gulnare." He also mentions an article that he expects from Van Schaick and a "Tale" from Mr. Bloodgood, presumably for The Legendary, 4 pages on 1 l., with typed transcript (6435) (Box-folder 12:29)
  - 1829 June 16 Nathaniel Parker Willis (1806-1867), Boston, to Colonel John B. Van Schaick, Albany, plans to go to Nahant with Miss Shaw, the Booths, Coolidges, etc. this afternoon, writes again about his problem with "Gulnare" who complained that his letters were "saucy" and disrespectful, and warns about associating with [Fred] Cobb, 3 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 12:29)
  - [1847?] February 3 Nathaniel Parker Willis (1806-1867) to Daniel Webster (1782-1852), invites him to participate in writing for the political department of his new magazine beginning publication in March, and has also invited Judge Story and Mr. Everett, saying "We do not wish to bend ourselves positively to any party, but the New England interest in politics is the one nearest our hearts, and we should be pleased if our magazine could be made an instrument to advocate & sustain it.", 2 pages on 1. (6435) (Box-folder 12:30)
  - n.d. Nathaniel Parker Willis (1806-1867) to "Dear Madam," verifies a story that she had heard about a fifty-five year old woman living in England who was convinced that Willis was the reincarnation of her betrothed killed in battle in the Peninsula, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 12:31)
  - 1855 January 25 Nathaniel Parker Willis (1806-1867) to "My dear Sir," replies that he has not seen the poem that he refers to in his letter, which possibly was opened and the poem rejected by the town office, 1 page, with typed transcript (6435) (Box-folder 12:32)
  - 1856 June 3 Nathaniel Parker Willis (1806-1867) to "My old friend," thanks him for his praise and the item sent to him for the magazine, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 12:32)
  - 1865 April 3 Nathaniel Parker Willis (1806-1867) to "Sir," writes during a period of extreme illness to assure him of his admiration for "The Lady Edith" which he sent immediately to the printer for "copy", 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 12:32)
  - n.d. Nathaniel Parker Willis (1806-1867) to "Dear Sir," expresses his nervousness at sending him his verses, as they were written while he was in college and he has lately been working on his essays, 2 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 12:32)
  - n.d. Nathaniel Parker Willis (1806-1867) engravings and calling card (6435) (Box-folder 12:33)
  - n.d. Nathaniel Parker Willis (1806-1867) autograph on a form letter from the Home Journal office, addressed to Edward Welles (6435) (Box-folder 12:34)
  - 1941 August 18 Wendell L. Willkie (1892-1944) to Charles A. Plumley (1875-1964), praises his speech, 1 typewritten page (6435-av) (Box-folder 12:35)
  - 1815 February 1 William Wirt (1772-1834) to Robert Taylor (1763-1845), congratulates him on his success in the appeal against Cole, with the court reversing the decree of the chancellor, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 12:36)
  - 1814 September 16 William Wirt (1772-1834), Camp Warrenigh Church, on the York River, to [Colonel Commanding?], requests permission to move their encampment from its present unhealthy position "to the field fronting above Tyrees, lately occupied by the cavalry, we shall avoid the damp & sickly ground on which our tents are now pitched, gain a firm & dry hill side, enjoy better water & equal contiguity to our training field." He also asks that their prolonges (a rope having a hook at one end and a toggle at the other, used to draw a gun carriage), be brought down from Richmond, 2 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 12:37)
  - n.d. William Wirt Notes said to be in his hand, 2 pages on 1 l. (6435-av) (Box-folder 12:38)
  - 1815 August 7 William Woods, of Albemarle County, Virginia, Autograph on Memorandum concerning pay due to several companies of Virginia Militia composing a part of General Robert Porterfield's Brigade stationed at Camp Holly near Richmond, Virginia, which is four months in arrears; mentions a letter from the district paymaster, Major Samuel Turner of Petersburg, dated in April saying that he did not have sufficient funds to pay the men., 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 12:39)
  - 1815 September 15 Noah Worcester (1758-1837) "Brighton's Apostle of Peace," one of the founders of American pacifism, to Thomas Arnold, promises to direct the publishers, Cummings and Hilliard, to forward 300 copies of the second number of the pacifist journal The Friend of Peace and encloses a copy of The Signal., 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 12:40)
  - 1860 May 15 Thomas C. Wright, to "My dear Kingsley," reports on the results of his inquiry about histories concerning Trinity House, an association of English mariners, discovering only one history, Memoir of the Original and Corporation of the Trinity House of Deptford (1818) by Cotton, and a copy of the "Charter of Incorporation given by James II" (1685) owned currently by Russell Smith. Joseph Cotton was appointed Deputy Master of Trinity House in 1803., 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 12:41)
  - 1860 September 18 Charlotte Mary Yonge (1823-1901) to "Gentlemen," sends the corrected proofs of "The Mice at Play" describing her ideas of the illustrations but recommends that the designer consult either Knights Old England or The Pictorial History of England for the costumes. 2 ¼ pages on 1 l., with an undated clipping about Yonge (6435-a) (Box-folder 12:42)
  - n.y. January 5 Charlotte Mary Yonge (1823-1901) to "Madam," writes on Monthly Packet stationery, "Your magician is very amusing, and shall be inserted when there is room - which is I fear the scarcest commodity in the Monthly Packet - it is a capital story and I am only puzzled by the names not being given to the police and so explaining things.", 2 pages on 1 l. (6435-a) (Box-folder 12:43)
  - n.y. October [24?] Charlotte Mary Yonge (1823-1901) to her cousin, "My dear Fanny" [F.W.W.], writes for more sources of information about the prophecies of Mother Shipton, [Ursula Southeil (c.1488-1561)], besides Chamber's Book of Days, plans to dine at Bishopstroke, Hampshire, to meet Sir Richard on Monday, with her cousins suggestion to ask Uncle Roland about Mother Shipton on the back of her letter., 4 pages on 1 l. (6435-a) (Box-folder 12:44)
  - 1829 October 23 Charles Mayne Young (1777-1856), for a time England's leading tragedian, to Mary Russell Mitford (1787-1855), who had written an original part for him in her play Rienzi, urges her to send him her manuscript [of a new play?] quickly, as "the knowledge which I have more intimate possession of than any other person, is the time requisite for me, in a new and important character, and the apprehension that it may be as the last extended time was a very long one.", 2 pages on 1 l. (6435-a) (Box-folder 12:45)